Three years ago, I was in misery because of my son. Then, a friend introduced
me to Jungto Society, and I recently finished 3 years of prayer.
Now, I am no longer miserable. My mind is very much at peace, and I am quite
happy.
My son is 29 years old.
When he started high school, he became very unhappy and began to stray because
he couldn’t handle the academic pressure.
He ended up dropping out of high school but somehow managed to get into college.
Even in college, he had a hard time and has been on and off terms.
At age 29, he is two months away from college graduation.
I think he's more at peace with himself than before.
But, maybe because of his accumulated karma, he seems to reproach himself
a lot and has a low self-esteem.
In two months, he'll have to graduate and get a job, but he seems to be very
anxious about it.
For now, I've been just observing him but I'm not sure if that's the right
thing to do, so I wanted to ask you what I need to do.
First, is your mind at ease or anxious when you observe your son?
I don't feel anxious about him anymore.
That's good.
But if you are uncomfortable with the way he is and wish him to be a certain
way, things won't turn out well.
But I worry that he has rather a pessimistic view about life, and…
Who? Your son? Now you are judging him.
Yes, but I am worried about his pessimistic attitude.
So, you want your son to be more optimistic about life.
You’re basically saying that you want him to be a certain way. You need to
stop doing that.
Then, I should just let him be...
Yes, but you want your son to be a certain way.
These days, is it easy or hard to get a job? It's hard.
Even the people with jobs are getting laid off these days, so you will
certainly have to worry about him getting a job.
If he manages to get a job, you'll have to worry about him getting married
and worry about him being rejected by good marriage candidates. The worries
are endless.
If he gets married, then you'll have to worry about him and his wife having
babies or the two of them getting into arguments.
Rather than worrying endlessly about your son, you should let him be as you
would a kid next door.
You should take it for granted that he won't get a job.
If he can get a job, great. If not, it's normal in the current economic
situation.
People are getting laid off, so getting a job is very hard.
Your son didn't even study hard. He took time off, so he is graduating from
college at 29 instead of early 20's like most people.
You are being greedy to expect your son to find a dream job and marry a dream
girl. Such wishes will only make you unhappy.
But what do you all wish for? You wish for the best spouses for your children
when they themselves are not the best.
You wish that your son get a good job even when he doesn't have the
qualifications for it.
If all these wishes came true, what would the world be like?
So what if your great son marries a woman who is less than ideal?
You should make up your mind to have people say how lucky your daughter-in-
law is to have married into your family.
If you run a business, make up your mind to hire less qualified people and be
a good boss, so they will all praise you.
Make up your mind to get a job, which will require you to work hard for little
pay, so that the boss will be happy to have such a good employee.
Do you ever think this way? Nobody here thinks this way, right?
When buying, you want to pay the lowest price, and when selling, you want to
sell for the highest price.
When buying a house, you are watching for the price to fall. When selling,
you are wondering when the price will peak.
How can the world always be as you wish?
I'm not saying that your son has problems.
Accept him as he is. If he were sick, you'd be worried, wouldn't you?
Be grateful that he is healthy.
There are a lot of people who dropped out of college or even high school.
At least, your son will be graduating from college.
For parents, even if your child is jobless, it is better for him to have
finished high school than to have dropped out of junior high, right?
There are many parents who say they wish nothing more than having their
children graduate from high school.
But your son will be a college graduate. How great is that?
Yes, I also think it's the Buddha's blessing.
So you should pray, “Thank you, Buddha, my son is healthy, and he finally
finished college. Thank you, thank you.”
Yes, I have been doing that.
That's good.
But my son frequently talks about becoming independent.
Yes?
That he wants to move out and live independently.
Then let him.
But he doesn't have any income yet.
Let him worry about that.
Let him move out and simply observe what he does.
He can't become independent because you cannot just let him be.
If he really wants to move out, can I find him a place to live?
That's up to you.
But you should know that, the more you help him, the worse off he will be.
For your son's sake, it's best for you not to help him.
Be aware that you are helping your son, not for your son's sake, but because
it hurts you to watch him struggle.
You are helping him because you can't bear not to.
So do I just continue praying as I have been?
Yes.
Thank you.
Love is caring for your children when they are young and detaching yourself from
them when they are older.
Love is just letting them live their lives.
But we lack the strength to just let them be.
You don't give them the care they need when they are young, and you don't have
the patience to let them be when they are older.
When your child falls down and cries, you have to let him be until he calms
down. But instead you rush over and make a fuss.
One moment, you are yelling at him for not listening to you. Then, when he
falls down, you lift him up in your arms and fuss over him.
Children do not learn their lesson this way. So, you have to be cool-headed.
If you really love your children, you need to be detached.
The greatest gift you can give your children is helping them become independent.
You must help them gain the strength to live on their own means.
This is the greatest gift that parents can give their children.
But you want to give your children money, which they may blow in no time.
When a person is independent, he can make a living on his own. He can find a
spouse for himself.
Getting divorced is not a problem. He can always find someone else to marry.
If his spouse dies, he can remarry.
But you raise you children like pets. You choose their college, pay their
tuition,
find them jobs, find them spouses, buy them houses, and even raise their kids.
You do this because you want to, so it's actually none of my business.
But it will make your life hard.
You will have to worry about your children until the day you die.
Even when you are 80 and your child is 50, you will worry about him constantly.
How will he live without me...
This is worse than how a bird lives.
You've been practicing for 3 years, and you're still worried about these
things?
You look happier though.
If you really love your son, you need to detach yourself from him.